Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts, 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0744.03
Manuscripts Division
- Series 1: Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts (C0744.03), 1570-1950; 82 boxes; 39 items
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 43: Homilies and Miracles of the Archangel Gabriel, and Various Marian Texts, 1870-1930; 43; 1 box Parchment. 123 folios, 2 columns, 15 lines. 1 sheet of paper inserted at the front of the mss, and 8 paper folios sewn into the manuscript between fols. 85-86. Woode
    - Letter in Amharic of Bālāmbārās Tasfā Māryām to Mamher Takla Haymānot, late 19th or early 20th century; 1 box (Box 43)
      With the sender's seal.
      On paper.
    - Homilies of the Archangel Gabriel for Tāhsās 22 and 19, late 19th or early 20th century; 1 box Folio 4r-28r (Box 43)
    - Nineteen Miracles of the Archangel Gabriel, late 19th or early 20th century; 1 box Folio 28r-76v (Box 43)
    - A Salām or Hymn of Salutation to the Archangel Gabriel, late 19th or early 20th century; 1 box Folio 77r-84r (Box 43)
    - Two Homilies and a Salām to the Virgin Mary, late 19th or early 20th century; 1 box Folio 88r-113 (Box 43)
    - Synaxarium Entry for Yakkātit 16 Celebrating the Virgin Mary Kidāna Mehrat (Covenant of Mercy), late 19th or early 20th century; 1 box Folio 114r-122r (Box 43)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 44: Gospel of John, 1770-1830; 44; 1 box Parchment. 79 folios, 2 columns, 18 lines. Wooden boards (split) with a hide case, and enclosed in a Western board book-shaped slipcase. Fols. 1r-2v, 79r-v are blank. 10 x 15 cm
    Former owner: Barakata Sellāsē.
    - Gospel of John, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-78 (Box 44)
    - A Short Prayer, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 78v (Box 44)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 45: Spiritual Discourses, late 19th or early 20th century; 45; 1 item Parchment. 54 folios, 1 column [fols. 2-8r, 2 columns [fols. 8v-29], 16-19 lines. Parchment covers, stitched and open spine. Fols. 1-2 and 53-54 are blank. 10.5 x 16.5 cm (Box 45)
    Spiritual discourses or sermons on the subject of love and biblical themes, in Amharic, fols. 3r-52v.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 46: The Book of Aragāwi Manfasāwi, 1800-1899; 46; 1 box Parchment. 283 folios, 2 columns, 16 lines. Wooden boards covered in stamped leather, stitched with leather spine. Fols. 1r and 283v are blank 13.5 x 15.5 cm
    Endnotes: note on the work, fol. 260v-r; other notes [different hands].
    - Thirty-Five Treatises or Discourses (dersān) by St. John Aragāwi Manfasāwi (John of Saba), 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-182r (Box 46)
    - Epistles by St. John Aragāwi Manfasāwi (John of Saba) on Spiritual Matters, 19th century; 1 box Folio 182r-260v (Box 46)
      (some numbered)
    - Further Unnumbered Discourses and Epistles, 19th century; 1 box Folio 260v-282r (Box 46)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 47: Gospel of John, 1700-1730; 47; 1 box Parchment. 92 folios, 2 columns, 14-15 lines. Wooden boards with parchment spine 14 x 16.5 cm
    Former owner: Abuna Hayla Māryām, replacing earlier owner's name.
    - A Prayer of Penitence, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 1v-2v (Box 47)
    - Gospel of John, Marked for Readings Each Day of the Week, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 3r-87v (Box 47)
    - List of Feast Days of Saints and Angels, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 88r-89r (Box 47)
    - A Prayer of Penitence Continued, early 18th century; 1 box Folio 89r-91r (Box 47)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 48: The Gospel of John, 19th century; 48; 1 item Parchment. 68 folios, 2 columns fols. 3-68, 19-20 lines, + 2 inserted folios (9.2 x 12 cm.) of miniatures. Wooden boards with stamped leather covering, leather spine, hide case with strap. Mirror insert inside front board, printed fabric insert inside back board. 10.5 x 15 cm (Box 48)
    Marked for readings on each day of the week, fols. 5r-70r.
    Two paintings, inserted later (20th century), protected by pieces of cloth:
    St. George and the Dragon, fol. 3v.
    The Virgin and Child, fol. 4r
    Endnotes: a blessing for a communicant, fols. 1r-2v. Medical prescription, fol. 2r-v.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 49: Antiphonary (Mawāse't), Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām), and Other Texts, 1800-1899; 49; 1 box Parchment. 78 folios, 2 columns, 16-20 lines. Wooden boards 14 x 15 cm
    Folios 76v-78b contain various pen trials; folios 1r and 61v are partially blank with pen trials.
    - Antiphonary (Mawāse't) for the Whole Year, 19th century; 1 box Folio 2r-29v (Box 49)
    - Salām or Hymn of Salutation to Agnātyos, 19th century; 1 box Folio 30r-32v (Box 49)
    - A List of Annual Festivals of the Ethiopian Church, 19th century; 1 box Folio 32v-33r (Box 49)
    - A Short Prayer to the Virgin Mary, 19th century; 1 box Folio 33r-v (Box 49)
    - A Composite Hymn Addressed to Various Saint, Including Inter Alia Petitions to God, the Virgin Mary, St. George and St. Michael, 19th century; 1 box Folio 34r-61r (Box 49)
    - The Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām), 19th century; 1 box Folio 62r-77r (Box 49)
    - A Short Andemta (Exegetical) Extract Concerning the Son, 19th century; 1 box Folio 77r-78r (Box 49)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 50: Psalter, 1800-1850; 50; 1 box Parchment. 183 folios, 1 column [fols. 1-158, 179-182], 2 columns [fols. 159-178], 16-19 lines. Wooden boards (split and repaired), stitched and open spine. 15 x 15 cm
    - Psalter, 1800-1850; 1 box
      - Psalms, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-137r (Box 50)
      - Canticles of the Prophets, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 137v-151v (Box 50)
      - Song of Songs, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 151v-158v (Box 50)
      - Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām) for Each Day of the Week, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 159r-174v (Box 50)
    - Various Prayers, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 174v-178v (Box 50)
    - A Prayer to Christ Incorporating a Portion of the Gospel of Matthew, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Smaller leave, 11.5 x 14cm (Box 50)
      [Different hand.]
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 51: Liturgical Miscellany, 1800-1830; 51; 1 box Parchment. 120 folios, 1 column, 14 lines. Leather covers, stitched and open spine. 1r-v, 2v, 69v, 120v are blank 7.5 x 15.5 cm
    - Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām) for Each Day of the Week, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-43r (Box 51)
    - Gate of Light ('Anqas'a Berhān, the second), Shorter office of the Virgin Mary, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 43r-59v (Box 51)
    - Malke' Hymn to the Virgin Mary, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 60r-82v (Box 51)
    - Malke' Hymn to Jesus Christ, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 82v-105v (Box 51)
    - Various Magic Prayers, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 105v-107r (Box 51)
      Different hands.
    - Malke' Hymn to St. Michael, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 107v-118v (Box 51)
    - A Fragment of a Song of Praise to Mary, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 119v-120r (Box 51)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 52: Ethiopic Psalter Fragment, 1800-1899; 52; 1 box; 2 items; Parchment. 114 folios, 1 column, 18 lines. No covers, stitched with open spine
    - Psalms, 19th century; 1 item
      Nos. 1-32 missing; leaf missing between fols. 83 and 84.
    - Canticles of the Prophets, 19th century; 1 box Folio 108v-114 (Box 52)
      Up to the Prayer of Hannah. Oonly fragment of the last leaf remaining.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 53: Theological Treatise on the Incarnation and Other Subjects, 1809; 53; 1 box Parchment. 59 folios, 2 columns, 19-21 lines. Wooden boards, stitched and open spine 11 x 15 cm
    Endnote: fol. 58v, a note stating that the manuscript was written in 1525 Era of the Martyrs and finished on T'eqemt 16 (equivalent to October 26 1809 AD), during the reign of King 'Egwāla S'eyon (r.1801-18).
    - A Theological Treatise in Amharic, Containing Various Sections On the Mystery of the Incarnation and the Mystery of the Trinity, early 19th century 1809; 1 box Folio 5r-35v (Box 53)
    - Epistles of the Patriarch Mark of Alexandria, Attempting to Refute the Various So-Called Heretical Views Held by the Parties of S'aggā (Grace), Qeb'at (Unction), and Sost Ledat (Three Births), early 19th century 1809; 1 box Folio 36r-58v (Box 53)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 54: Liturgical Miscellany, 1830-1870; 54; 1 box Parchment. 36 folios, 1 column, 12-14 lines. Wooden boards (front board partly missing), stitched with open spine. 11 x 15.5 cm
    Endnotes: various pen trials and scribbles, fols. 1r-2v; various contracts of sale, fols.34v-35r; prayers and further notes of contract and letters, fols. 35v-36v.
    Former owner: Walda Kidān.
    - Malke' Hymn to the Trinity, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-16v (Box 54)
    - Malke' Hymn to St. Takla Haymānot, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 17r-30v (Box 54)
    - Salām Hymn to Assumption of the Virgin Mary, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 30v-34 (Box 54)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 55: The Gospel of John, early 19th century; 55; 1 item Parchment. 86 folios, 2 columns, 16 lines. Wooden boards covered with red leather, with spine of the same. Fols. 1r-2v and 86v are blank 10 x 13 cm (Box 55)
    Gospel of John, marked for reading on each day of the week, fols. 3r-86r.
    Decorative harag (headpiece) in black and red, fol 3r.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 56: Liturgical and Other Texts, 1750-1799; 56; 1 box Parchment. 86 folios, 2 columns [fols. 1r-40r, 63r-81v], 1 column [fols. 41r-62v], 12-18 lines. Wooden boards. Fols. 26v, 40v, 82r-86v are blank. 11 x 14 cm
    Drawings:
    Small talismanic drawing, fol. 40r.
    Former owners: Semrata 'Ab, Mahtama Qeddest Sellāsē (both in later sections).
    - Fragment of the Life of St. George (Gadla Giyorgis), second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 1r-2v (Box 56)
    - Hymns to the Trinity and Mary from the Sebhata Nagh (Praise to the Morning, or Matins), second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 3r-26r (Box 56)
      Beginning in abrupto, beginning missing.
    - Hymns to the Virgin Mary, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 27r-36v (Box 56)
      Different late 18th-century hand.
    - Fragment, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 37r-38v (Box 56)
      Beginning and finishing in abrupto.
    - Prayer against Hail and Wind, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 39r-40r (Box 56)
    - Various Extracts from the Liturgy, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 41r-61v (Box 56)
    - Two Prayers, One against Wild Animals and One against Headache, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 62r-v (Box 56)
      19th-centuryhands. The prayer against headache is in red.
    - Part of the Liturgy Addressed to the Virgin Mary, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 63r-77r (Box 56)
    - Prayers against Hail, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 77r-78v (Box 56)
    - A Further Liturgical Fragment, second half of the 18th century; 1 box Folio 79r-81v (Box 56)
      Beginning in abrupto.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 57: Liturgical Miscellany, 1700-1799; 57; 1 box Parchment. 90 folios, 1 column, 12-13 lines. Wooden boards with plain cloth slipcover. Fols. 88r-90v are blank 10 x 13.5 cm
    Fols. 1-2 consist of a folded leaf taken from an earlier manuscrip.t
    Former owner: Gabra Sellāsē.
    - Malke' Hymn to the Trinity, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 3r-14v (Box 57)
    - Prayer to Christ for Deliverance from Slander, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 15r-25r (Box 57)
    - Malke' Hymn to St. George, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 25v-37v (Box 57)
    - Prayer for Intercession of the Virgin Mary and St. George, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 37v-48r (Box 57)
    - Prayer of the Virgin Mary at Golgotha, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 48r-67r (Box 57)
    - Prayer to the Cross, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 67r-70r (Box 57)
    - Prayer against Hail, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 70r-v (Box 57)
    - Malke' Hymn to St. Takla Haymānot, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 71r-80v (Box 57)
    - Malke' Hymn to the Virgin Mary, late 18th century; 1 box Folio 80v-87v (Box 57)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 58: Liturgical Miscellany, 1830-1850; 58; 1 box Parchment. 58 folios, 1 column, 15-19 lines. Front parchment cover, no back cover, stitched and open spine 10 x 14 cm
    Endnote: land contract during the reign of Yohannes IV (r. 1871-89), fol. 46r.
    Front cover counted as fol. 1.
    - T'abiba T'abibān ("the Wisest of the Wise", a Hymn of Praise To God), mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 2r-29v (Box 58)
    - Malke' Hymn to the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 30r-46r (Box 58)
    - Supplication Prayer ('esagged) to the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 47v-49v (Box 58)
    - Three Miracles of the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 49v-54v (Box 58)
    - A Miracle of the Child Jesus, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 54v-56v (Box 58)
    - A Miracle of the Archangel Michael, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 56v-58v (Box 58)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 59: Lenten Antiphonary, 19th century; 59; 1 item Parchment. 38 folios, 2 columns, 11-17 lines. No covers, stitched with open spine. Folios 23v, 24r are blank. Text: 11 x 14 cm (Box 59)
    Fragments of the S'oma Deggwā or Service for Lent, with cantillation signs, fols. 1v-38r. [Various hands]
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 60: Ge'ez Grammar Book (Sawāsew), late 19th century; 60; 1 item Parchment. 18 folios, 1 column, 21-23 lines. No covers, loosely sewn. Fol. 1r is blank 8.5 x 13.5 cm (Box 60)
    Ge'ez grammar book in Amharic, incomplete, fols. 1v-18v. Ending in abrupto.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 61: Doctrina Arcanorum, and Other Liturgical Texts, 1830-1870; 61; 1 box 32 folios, 2 columns, 16 lines. Wooden boards, stitched with open spine. Fols. 1r-2, 30v-32v are blank 10 x 13.5 cm
    - Doctrina Arcanorum (Temherta Hebu'āt), mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-9v (Box 61)
    - Malke' Hymn to the Savior of the World, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 9v-17v (Box 61)
    - Petition Hymn (sa'al lana) to the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 17v-23v (Box 61)
    - Petition Hymn (sa'al lana) to St. George, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 23v-26v (Box 61)
    - Petition Hymn (sa'al lana) to Ss. Michael and Gabriel, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 26v (Box 61)
    - Hymn for the Intercession of Jesus, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 26v-30r (Box 61)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 62: Psalter, 1800-1850; 62; 1 box Parchment. 191 folios, 1 column [fols. 1r-175v], 2 columns [fols. 176r-191v], 16-17 lines. Wooden board (front), back board missing, stitched with open spine. 12.5 x 12.0 cm
    Endnotes: list of saints' feast days, fol. 190v; prayer to Mary, fols. 190v-191v.
    - Psalms, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-150v (Box 62)
      (incomplete, nos. 1-10 are missing)
    - Canticles of the Prophets, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 150v-168v (Box 62)
    - Song of Songs, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 168v-175v (Box 62)
    - Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām) for the Seven Days of the Week, first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 176r-185r (Box 62)
    - Second office of the Virgin Mary ('Anqas'a Berhān or Gate of Light), first half of the 19th century; 1 box Folio 185r-190r (Box 62)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 63: Collection of Malke' Hymns, and Other Texts, 1800-1830; 63; 1 box Parchment. 79 folios, 2 columns, 15 lines. Wooden boards (split and repaired), stitched with open spine. Fol. 79v is blank. 11.5 x 12.5 cm
    Endnotes: fragments of a hymn to the Virgin Mary, fol. 1r-, 47v; magic prayer, fol. 79r.
    - Malke' Hymn to the Virgin Mary, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 2r-12v (Box 63)
    - Malke' Hymn to Jesus Christ, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 12v-22r (Box 63)
    - Malke' Hymn to the Archangel Michael, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 22r-30v (Box 63)
    - Malke' Hymn to the Archangel Gabriel, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 30v-35r (Box 63)
    - Malke' Hymn to St. Takla Haymānot, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 35r-45r (Box 63)
    - Prayer to St. John the Evangelist, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 45r (Box 63)
      Incomplete. Different hand.
    - Calendrical Treatise on the Days and Nights of a Month, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 45v-46v (Box 63)
    - Medical Prescription, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 46v-47v (Box 63)
    - Life and Miracles of St. Gabra Manfas Qeddus, Along With Salām Hymns to the Same, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 48r-79r (Box 63)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 64: Malke' Hymn and Doctrina Arcanorum, 1700-1799; 64; 1 box Parchment. 46 folios, 1 column, 10-11 lines. Parchment covers, stitched with open spine 9 x 12.5 cm
    Parchment covers are counted as fol. 1 and fol. 46. Endnotes: the Credo (Na'ammen), fols. 2r-3r; two prayers, fol. 3v; magic prayers, fol. 4r-v; the beginning of the Gospel of John, fols. 43v-44r; another magic prayer, fols. 44r-45v.
    - Malke' Hymn to the Trinity, 18th century; 1 box Folio 5r-30r (Box 64)
    - Doctrina Arcanorum (Temherta Hebu'āt), 18th century; 1 box Folio 30r-43r (Box 64)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 65: Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām), 1800-1899; 65; 1 box Parchment. 54 folios, 2 columns, 15 lines. Wooden boards, stitched with open spine. Fols. 1r-2v, 54v are blank 10 x 12.5 cm
    - Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām) Marked for the Seven Days of the week), 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-51 (Box 65)
      In different modes and with cantillation signs, followed in continuo by other liturgical pieces.
    - List of Halleluiahs, 19th century; 1 box Folio 51r-54r (Box 65)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 66: Prayer of Mary at Golgotha and Doctrina Arcanorum, 1830-1870; 66; 1 box Parchment with some paper [fols. 4-7, 10-13, 16-19, 22-25], 9 x 12 cm. 45 folios, 1 column, 11-12 lines. Wooden boards (split and repaired), stitched with open spine. Fols. 1r-2v, 43v, 45r-v are blank. 9 x 12 cm
    Former owner: Gabra Mikā'ēl.
    - Prayer of Mary at Golgotha, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 3r-33r (Box 66)
    - Doctrina Arcanorum (Temherta Hebu'āt), mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 33v-44r (Box 66)
    - Invocation for Salvation in He Name of the Owner, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 44v (Box 66)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 67: Miracles of St. Gabra Manfas Qeddus, early 18th century; 67; 1 item Parchment. 88 folios, 1 column, 10 lines. Hide cover (front only), stitched with open spine. Fols. 1r-2v are blank. 7.5 x 12 cm (Box 67)
    Twelve Miracles of St. Gabra Manfas Qeddas, fols. 3r-88v (terminates in abrupto).
    Note the occasional archaic form of the letter 'lo', which is normally thought to have gone out of use by the middle of the 16th century.
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 68: Collection of Hymns, 1600-1699; 68; 1 box; 2 items; Parchment. 36 folios, 2 columns, 11-12 lines. No covers, stitched, fol. 1 detached
    - Extensive Hymn of Praise to the Virgin Mary, 17th century; 1 box Folio 1r-28r (Box 68)
      (beginning in abrupto)
    - Three Malke' Hymns to the Virgin Mary, 17th century; 1 box Folio 28r-32v (Box 68)
    - Salām Hymn to the Angels Michael, Gabriel, Raphael, Uriel, Phanuel, Raguel, Sachael (Sāqu'ēl), Sariel (Sureyāl) and the Ophanim, Together With the Four Beasts or Zoa, the Twenty Four Priests of Heaven, the Ten Thousand Watchers, the Eleven Apostles (sic, and St. George), 17th century; 1 item
      (terminates in abrupto)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 69: Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām), 1830-1870; 69; 1 box Parchment. 95 folios, 2 columns, 10-12 lines. Wooden boards with cloth slipcover, stitched with cloth covered spine 9 x 10.5 cm
    Fols. 1 and 95 are pieces cut from an older (18th century) manuscript used as flyleaves.
    - Praise of Mary (Weddāsē Māryām) Marked for Each of the Days of the Week, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 2r-54r (Box 69)
    - Gate of Light ('Anqas'a Berhān), the Second, Shorter office of the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 54r-73r (Box 69)
    - Salām Hymn to the Assumption of the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 73v-78v (Box 69)
    - Extensive Hymn of Praise to the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 78v-92r (Box 69)
    - Prayer of Intercession Through the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 92r-94v (Box 69)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 70: Various Prayers and Doctrina Arcanorum, 1800-1870; 70; 1 box Parchment. 56 folios, 2 columns, 12-15 lines. No covers, stitched 11 x 12.5 cm
    Former owner: name erased throughout.
    - Series of Prayers for Compassion in Continuo Addressed Variously To God and to Jesus Christ, early 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-12r (Box 70)
    - Doctrina Arcanorum (Temherta Hebu'āt), mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 12v-19 (Box 70)
    - Prayer of Mary at Golgotha, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 19r-35v (Box 70)
    - Prayer for the Intercession of the Virgin Mary, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 35v-48r (Box 70)
    - Prayer to Mary Invoking the Passion of Christ, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 49r-56r (Box 70)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 71: Liturgical Miscellany, 1770-1830; 71; 1 box Parchment. 48 folios, 1 column, 10-16 lines. No covers, stitched, with hide slipcase 7 x 10 cm
    - Prayer of Intercession or Supplication, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-14r (Box 71)
      (beginning missing)
    - Hymn to the Virgin Mary, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 14r-31v (Box 71)
    - Hymn to Jesus Christ, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 31v-36r (Box 71)
    - Various Prayers and Admonitions against Temptations of the Flesh, etc, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 36r-40v (Box 71)
    - Fragment of the Kidān Zanagh or Morning Covenant, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 41r-48v (Box 71)
      (terminates in abrupto, end missing)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 72: Prayer of Apostles for the Remission of Sin & the Cross, 1830-1870; 72; 1 box Parchment. 45 folios, 1 column, 10-15 lines. Hide covers with printed fabric slipcover, stitched 7 x 12 cm
    Former owner: Hayla Sellāsē, inserted over erasures of earlier name.
    - Prayer Attributed to the Apostles for the Remission of Sins, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-27v (Box 72)
    - Synaxarium Entry for St. Roqo for Miyāzyā 23, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 27v-30r (Box 72)
    - Prayer of the Cross, mid 19th century; 1 box Folio 30r-45v (Box 72)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 73: Anaphora of the Apostle John and Other Texts, 1770-1830; 73; 1 box Parchment. 70 folios, 1 column, 11-12 lines. Hide covers, stitched with open spine 9 x 12 cm
    Former owner: Walda Tensā'ē (not the original owner.)
    - Anaphora of the Apostle John ('Akwatēta Qwerbān Zaqeddus Yohannes Hawāryā), late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 1r-32 (Box 73)
    - Anaphora of the Three Hundred and Eighteen Orthodox ('Akwatēta Qwerbān Za-310 Wa-8 Retu'āna Haymānot), late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 32r-59r (Box 73)
    - Malke' Hymn to St. John Boanerges, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 59r-69r (Box 73)
    - Prayer to Jesus, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 69r (Box 73)
    - Prayer for Those Who Participate in the Eucharistic Communion, late 18th or early 19th century; 1 box Folio 69v-70v (Box 73)
  - Garrett Ethiopic Manuscript No. 74: Psalter, 1670-1899; 74; 1 box Parchment. 190 folios, 1 column [fols. 1r-177r], 2 columns [fols. 178r-186r], 13-16 lines. Hide covers, stitched with open spine. Folios 1r-3v and 26v are blank. 9.5 x 10.0 cm
    Fols. 1-39 are 19th century, replacing missing portions of the older, late 17th century text.
    Pen trials, fols. 2v-3v.
    - Psalms, late 17th century with extensive 19th century additions; 1 box Folio 4r-155v (Box 74)
    - Canticles of the Prophets, late 17th century; 1 box Folio 156r-173r (Box 74)